Guide to the Lambiotte Family/Francis Poulenc archive, 1920-1994 MS 623
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Lambiotte Family/Francis Poulenc archive
1920-1994
1920-1963
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963
MS 623
4 Linear Feet (6 document boxes, one oversize box, one oversize file in map drawer)
3.16 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0623aip_001 (3.16 GB)
The Lambiotte Family/Francis Poulenc archive contains materials that document Poulenc's life and career during his long friendship with the Lambiotte family, a Belgian family with close ties of friendship to the composer. The collection includes autograph musical manuscripts, signed and inscribed printed musical scores, letters, photographs, publications, and ephemera. Dates for the collection range from 1920 to 1994, with bulk dates from 1920 to 1963.
Biographical / Historical
Francis Jean Marcel Poulenc (January 1, 1899-January 30, 1963) was an accomplished French composer and pianist known for his mélodies, solo piano works, chamber music, orchestral works, choral pieces, operas, and ballets. Poulenc was a member of Les Six, a group of French and Swiss composers who had links with Erik Satie, Jean Hugo and Jean Cocteau.
"Francis Poulenc has come to be considered the greatest composer of French mélodies of his period – a period that opened with the aftermath of the First World War and closed as recently as 1960. He set to music poetry by all of the greatest French twentieth century poets, as well as a few from earlier times. For 25 years the famous baritone Pierre Bernac, with Poulenc at the piano, toured Europe giving recitals, and also visited Britain and America. Thanks to their work, not only in the French repertoire but also in the general Lieder repertoire, the piano-accompanied song increased enormously in popularity in their own country; and in other countries they were very largely responsible for the present wide popularity of the French song repertoire." Exerpt from: Bernac: "Francis Poulenc: The Man and his Songs"
Pierre Bernac (January 12, 1899-October 17, 1979) was a French singer who became the most renowned interpreter of the French art song. He had a close artistic association with Francis Poulenc, who wrote many of his songs for Bernac. He gave the first performances of Francis Poulenc's "Chansons gaillardes" in 1926. He began appearing in recital with Poulenc as his accompanist in 1934, and they continued performing together until Bernac withdrew from performing in public about 1960.
Denise Duval (October 23, 1921- January 25, 2016) was a French soprano, best known for her performances in works by the composer Francis Poulenc. Duval created the roles of Elle in "La voix humaine," Thérèse in "Les mamelles de Tirésias" and later sang the role of Blanche de la Force in "Dialogues of the Carmelites."
Richard Chanlaire (1896-1973) was a French painter, known as the first serious lover of composer Francis Poulenc. Chanlaire exhibited regularly in Paris: at the Salon de la Société Nationale des Beaux-Arts, the Salon des Tuileries, and the Salon des Artistes Indépendants. Chanlaire also designed for collections of Christian Dior and Pierre Balmain.
Scope and Contents
The Lambiotte Family/Francis Poulenc archive contains materials that document Poulenc's life and career during his long friendship with the Lambiotte family, a Belgian family with close ties of friendship to the composer. The collection includes autograph musical manuscripts, signed and inscribed printed musical scores, letters, photographs, publications, and ephemera. Dates for the collection range from 1920 to 1994, with bulk dates from 1920 to 1963.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored on-site at the Woodson Research Center inside vault.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lambiotte Family/Francis Poulenc archive was acquired from the family of Madame Rose Lambiotte, long-time friend of the composer, in 2015.
Index Terms
Subjects
Music--France--20th century; Composition (Music); Groupe des Six (Group of composers); Composers--France; Music
Document Types
letters (correspondence); programs (documents); photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Bernac, Pierre; Chanlaire, Richard; Duval, Denise; Lambiotte family
- Series I: Autograph musical manuscripts/scores, 1929 and undated; 212362
  - Concert champêtre pour clavecin (ou piano) et orchestra. [FP 49], 1929; 212451 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    The complete reduced score, used by the printer for publication. [2] (title) + 34 + [10 (blank) + 11 + [1] (blank) + 30 + 1 ("Fin Nouvelle") + [2] (blank) pp. Folio. Notated in black and red inks. Some annotations in pencil; occasional erasures and minor corrections. Dedicated to Wanda Landowska. White vellum. With autograph letter from Poulenc to Richard Chanlaire dated May 10, 1929 incorporating 4-bar autograph musical quotation.
  - Aubade Concerto chorégraphique pour piano et dix-huit instruments. [FP 51], 212452 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A working draft. 49 + iv (titles) + [2] (blank) pp. Folio. Notated in pencil on 58 leaves with titling in ink. Written on one side of the leaf only on music manuscript paper with "1106" at lower right margin of some leaves. Many leaves guarded at inner margin. Black boards. Together with an autograph letter from Poulence laid in. An important manuscript demonstrating the creative process.
  - Aubade Concerto chorégraphique pour piano et dix-huit instruments. [FP 51], 212457 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Two-piano reduction. [2] (title) + 42 + [7] (blank) pp. Folio. Notated in blue, black and red inks. Some corrections and erasures; several additions in pencil; slight smudging where corrections were executed. Black boards.
  - Nocturne [no. 1 in C major for piano]. [FP 56 – 1], 212458 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Used by the printer for publication. [1] (title) + 6 + [1] (blank) pp. Folio. Notated in black ink. Some erasures. Black boards. There are 8 Nocturnes in the series. The only known autograph of the work.
  - Quatre poems de Guillaume Apollinaire pour baryton (ou mezzo) et piano. [FP 58], 212459 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [2] + 15 + [3] (blank) pp. Folio. Notated in ink. Some autograph corrections in pencil. Black boards. The only known autograph of the work.
  - Cinq poèmes de Max Jacob. No. 5. Souric et Mouric. [FP 59 – 5], 212460 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    4 pp. Folio. Notated in black ink. A few erasures. Slightly browned. Dedication changed to 'Curie." Black boards.
  - Une chanson de porcelaine. [FP 169], 212461 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Used by the printer for publication. 1f. (recto title, verso text of poem) + [2] + [2] (blank) pp. Folio. One erasure. With envelope. Black boards.
  - Improvisation [13] en la mineur. [FP 170], 212462 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    [2] (title) + 3 + 1 (blank) pp. Folio. With occasional erasures and additions. Black boards. Together with a 2-page autograph letter signed. The only known autograph of the work.
  - Laudes de Saint Antoine de Padoue. [FP 172], 212463 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    For male chorus a cappella Used by the printer for publication. [2] (title) + 10 pp. Folio. Score. 4 numbers, complete, each dated. With short sketch to verso of title. Embossed stamp of "Flammarion Magasin de Musique" to foot of first page of music, plate number to foot of some pages. With several minor corrections. Date to title and some annotations apparently added at a later date. Black boards. The only known autograph of the work.
  - Improvisation [15] en ut mineur. [FP 176], 212464 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [2] + 4 + 2 pp. Folio. A few minor corrections and erasures. With an inscription signed "Poupoule" (Poulenc's nickname); also signed "Francis Poulenc." Dedicated to Edith Piaf. Black boards. The only known autograph of the work.
- Series II: Signed and inscribed printed musical scores, 1920-1958; 212363
  - Airs chantés, 212455 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Green boards. [1] (title), 2-19 pp. Copyright 1928, 1930. Slightly browned.
  - Le Bestiare, 212456 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Black cloth with printed wrappers bound in. 8 pp. Copyright 1920. Inscribed Poulenc's friend, the musicologist Pierre Aubry.
  - Cocardes, 212465 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Black cloth. 1f. (title) + 10 pp. Copyright 1920. With a long autograph inscription to first page of music signed.
  - Deux Poèmes d'Aragon, 212466 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Green boards. [1] (title), 2-7 pp. Copyright 1944. With offset from inscription to verso of free front endpaper. Browned and slightly brittle.
  - Fiançailles pour rire (2 copies), 212468 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    Green boards. [1] (title), 2-19 pp. Copyright 1940. Slightly browned
  - Métamorphoses, 212470 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Green boards. 1f. (title), 9 pp. PN R.L. 12, 174, copyright 1944. Browned and brittle; offsetting to verso of free front endpaper.
  - Montparnasse et Hyde Park, 212471 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Green boards with printed wrappers bound in. 7 pp. Copyright 1945.
  - À Sa Guitare, 212473 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Green boards. [1] (title), 2-3 pp. music. Copyright 1935. Browned. Not inscribed.
  - Tel jour telle nuit, 212474 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Original printed wrappers. 1f. (title), 1f. (index), 23 pp. Copyright 1937. Slightly browned.
  - 13e Improvisation en la mineur, 212476 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Black cloth. 1f. (title), 4 pp. Copyright 1958. Slightly browned. Together with another copy laid in, copyright 1958, and a copy of the 15e Improvisation, copyright 1960, neither of the additional copies inscribed.
  - Trois Chansons de F. García Lorca, 212477 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Green boards. [1] (title), 2-9 pp. Copyright 1947. Slightly browned.
- Series III: Publications, 1927-1974; 212368
  - Six Poesies de Jean Cocteau by Arthur Honegger, 212453 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Paris: Senart [PN E.M.S. 6602], copyright 1924.
    Poems include: i. La nègre ii. Locutions iii. Souvenirs d'enfance iv. Ex voto v. Une danseuse vi. Madame
    Folio. Black boards with leather title label, original wrappers printed in blue bound in with original drawing to upper and with autograph inscription by Honegger: "pour Hilde son Arthur." Title heavily illustrated in ink by both Poulenc and Honegger and with autograph inscription to Hilde Gélis-Didot signed by Poulenc and dated "[?] Steredenn Vor 1927." [1] (title), 2-11, [1] (blank) pp. Browned. Some offsetting to page 2 (title). Spratt 45 (p. 520).
  - Entretiens avec Claude Rostand, 212454 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Paris: Juilliard [1954]. With inscription to half title.
  - Poulenc: Musicien Français par Henri Hell, 212479 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Inscribed by Poulenc, 1958.
  - Prayers and Graces: a little book of extraordinary piety, Collected by Allan M. Liang., 1944; 212480 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Inscribed to Madame Auguste Lambiotte by Poulenc, Christmas 1945.
  - Poulenc et Rocamadour, 1974; 212961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Emmanuel Chabrier, 1961; 212481 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Inscribed by Poulenc.
  - Francis Poulenc: Journal de mes Mélodies, 1964; 212482 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - La Revue des Deux Mondes, 1963; 212483 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Aubade Concerto chorégraphique pour piano et dix-huit instruments (printed score), 1931; 212484 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Francis Poulenc Improvisations pour le piano. XIVème Improvisation en ré bémol majeur (printed score), 1958; 242312 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Correspondence (Poulenc and Lambiotte family), 1946-1962, undated; 212364
  An important archive consisting of approximately 100 letters (approximately 225 pages) spanning the years 1946 to 1962. The correspondence relates to musical matters including Poulenc's own works and performances and performers of such, other composers, reminiscences, travel plans, and, at times, personal commentary regarding his attitudes, friends and associates, etc. The materials present a comprehensive overview offering significant insight into Poulenc's life, both as composer and individual, over some 16 years.
  The primary recipients of the letters are Madame Rose Lambiotte (1891-1964), sometimes referred to in the correspondence as "Mme. Chapdelaine," her daughter Rosine, and, occasionally, Rose's husband Auguste Lambiotte. The family lived in Belgium and Poulenc often stayed with them, referring to them as "his Belgian family." The correspondence files include letters as well as cards, photographs, and newsclippings which were included in the correspondence.
  - Subseries A: Poulenc to Madame Rose Lambiotte, 238399; (58 letters)
    General
    Correspondence from Francis Poulenc to Madame Rose Lambiotte. Some letters contain copies of the response of Madame Lambiotte to Poulenc.
    - 1946, 238400 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1947, 238401 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1948-1951, 238402 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1953-1955, 238403 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1958-1959, 238404 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1960-1961, undated, 238405 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: Poulenc to Madame de Chapdelaine (Madame Rose Lambiotte), 238406; (25 letters)
    Correspondence from Francis Poulenc to Madame Rose Lambiotte as "Madame Chapdelaine." Some letters contain copies of the response of Madame Lambiotte to Poulenc.
    - 1949-1955, 238562 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1956-1959, 238563 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1960-1962, undated, 238564 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Subseries C: Madame de Chapdelaine (Madame Rose Lambiotte) to Poulenc, 238573; (7 letters)
    - 1949-1962, undated, 238574 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Subseries D: Poulenc to Monsieur Auguste Lambiotte, 238744; (9 letters)
    - 1949-1959, undated, 238746 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Subseries E: Poulenc to Famille Lambiotte (Monsieur and Madame), 238745; (11 letters)
    - 1946-1960, 238798 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Subseries F: Poulenc to Mademoiselle Rosine Lambiotte (Titon), 239066; (3 letters)
    - 1954-1956, 239067 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Subseries G: Poulenc to Paige and Rosine Lambiotte Donhouser, 239271; (3 letters)
    - 1960-1962, 239272 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series V: Correspondence (Bernac and Lambiotte family, other correspondence), 1944-1990, undated; 239273
  The series consists of 28 letters and notes spanning the years 1944 to 1990, with a copy of a letter from the Poulenc brothers dated 1893. Most of the correspondence is from Pierre Bernac, the great interpreter of Poulenc's vocal works, to the Lambiotte family. The primary recipients of the letters are Madame Rose Lambiotte (1891-1964), sometimes referred to in the correspondence as "Mme. Chapdelaine," and her daughter Rosine Lambiotte Donhauser. The series includes letters as well as cards and telegrams which were included in the correspondence.
  - Subseries A: Bernac to Madame Rose Lambiotte, 239274; (15 letters)
    Correspondence from Piere Bernac to Madame Rose Lambiotte. Some letters contain copies of the response of Madame Lambiotte to Bernac.
    - 1944-1954, 239313 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1956-1963, undated, 239314 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: Bernac to Madame de Chapdelaine (Madame Rose Lambiotte), 239275; (2 letters)
    - 1949-1950, 239315 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries C: Bernac to Rosine Lambiotte Donhauser, 239276; (2 letters)
    - 1963-1966, 239316 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subseries D: Other correspondence, 239317; (9 letters)
    - 1950-1990, 239318 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Photographs, 1945-1961, undated; 212365
  The series includes four undated images of Poulenc and Bernac performing in concert; one photo (1945) of Poulenc reviewing materials with Bernac; a 1960 photo of Poulenc and Denise Duval, signed by both; a photo of Poulenc in Noizay (1961); a photo of Denise Duval in a garden (1991); and photo of Poulenc's country home in Noizay, ca. 1950.
  - 1945-1961, undated, 239472 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Ephemera, 1947-1994, undated; 212366
  Includes painted silk scarf with music manuscript as part of design, programs, messages, letters and listings of Poulenc manuscript holdings and sales
  - Scarf designed by Richard Chanlaire for Pierre Balmain, design includes music by Poulenc, signed to "Madame Cha Cha" (Rose Lambiotte), October 1952; 213988 (Map-drawer 31, Folder 2)
  - Messages for Poulenc and Bernac from Madame Lambiotte, 1947; 242317 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Program, Concours Musical International Reine Elisabeth de Belgique, with Poulenc on jury and notes in back (2 copies), 1960; 242315 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Program, Carnegie Hall 1962-1963 season, with Poulenc composers showcase (in memory) and added program insert, 242316 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Program, L'Eremurus Hommage à Francis Poulenc, 1963; 242318 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Program, Philharmonic Hall, Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, 1963; 242319 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Program, Saison Musicale de Royaumont in memory of Poulenc (2 copies), 1963; 242313 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Program, "Figure Humaine", Poulenc lyrics, (Dutch and French), undated; 242320 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Les Amis de Francis Poulenc, letter by Bernac and cards, undated; 242321 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photocopy, Manuscript of "Mazurka" for Doda Conrad in Poulenc's hand, undated; 242314 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Program, Doda Conrad recital, Carnegie Hall, 1960; 242322 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Letters, listings of Poulenc manuscript holdings and sale information, 1961-1994, undated; 242323 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Librairie de l'Abbaye catalogue, Autographes 1435-1953, 1961; 242324 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Series VIII: Newsclippings, 1920-1993; 212367
  The series includes critical response to debut performances of Poulenc's works; homages to his influence on 20th century neoclassical music; and obituaries.
  - Newsclippings from French and English publications (primariy French), 1920-1993; 242311 (Box 7, Folder 1)